<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catholicon, the expediency of an explicit stipulation betwixt the parochial ministers and their congregations, or, An essay to prove that the intervention of solemn mutual promises betwixt the parochial ministers and their people (faithfully to discharge their relative duties to one another) would be useful and expedient for these ends to promote in clergy-men regularity of life, and diligence in their ministerial function, to increase in the lay parishioners, Christian knowledge, sincere godliness, with a free and friendly conversation, to give a stop to separation, and reduct dissenters to the communion of the church without using secular compulsion, to secure the peace of the nation, to inlarge trade, and make provision for the poor, and that all may be effected without the least innovation, or alteration of the present legal establishment of the Church of England humbly tendred to the consideration of all English Protestants / by a parochial minister.</title>
            <author>Parochial minister.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12394940</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12394940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 933:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catholicon, the expediency of an explicit stipulation betwixt the parochial ministers and their congregations, or, An essay to prove that the intervention of solemn mutual promises betwixt the parochial ministers and their people (faithfully to discharge their relative duties to one another) would be useful and expedient for these ends to promote in clergy-men regularity of life, and diligence in their ministerial function, to increase in the lay parishioners, Christian knowledge, sincere godliness, with a free and friendly conversation, to give a stop to separation, and reduct dissenters to the communion of the church without using secular compulsion, to secure the peace of the nation, to inlarge trade, and make provision for the poor, and that all may be effected without the least innovation, or alteration of the present legal establishment of the Church of England humbly tendred to the consideration of all English Protestants / by a parochial minister.</title>
                  <author>Parochial minister.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61103:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Catholicon</p>
            <p>THE EXPEDIENCY OF AN EXPLICIT STIPULATION BETWIXT THE Parochial Miniſters AND THEIR CONGREGATIONS.</p>
            <p>OR, An ESSAY to prove that the Intervention of Solemn Mutual Promiſes betwixt the Parochial Miniſters and their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>(Faithfully to diſcharge their Relative Duties to one another)</hi> would be uſeful and expedient for theſe ends:</p>
            <list>
               <item>To promote in Clergy-men Regularity of Life, and Diligence in their Miniſterial Function.</item>
               <item>To increaſe in the Lay Pariſhioners, Chriſtian Knowledge, Sincere Godlineſs, with a Free and Friendly Converſation.</item>
               <item>To give a Stop to Separation, and Reduce Diſſenters to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church without uſing Secular Compulſion.</item>
               <item>To ſecure the Peace of the Nation.</item>
               <item>To inlarge Trade, and make Proviſion for the Poor.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And that all this may be effected without the leaſt Innovation, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the preſent Legal Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly tendred to the Conſideration of all Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, by a Parochial Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed. 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:61103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61103:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>I Intend not in this Treatiſe to give Rules to any of my Brethren, much leſs to preſcribe to Authority; But I preſume that ſo far as the Holy Scriptures, and the Laws of the Land, and ſound Prudence appear on the ſide of my undertaking, it will find peaceable reception with all, who adhere yet to the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England:</hi> and I deſire no man to admit it further, than that warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is annexed.</p>
            <p>And it being deſigned only to promote the good ends men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Title-page: I may expect that it will not find a bitter Adverſary, if any, amongſt the Diſſenters from the Order of Worſhip and Diſcipline legally eſtabliſhed amongſt us.</p>
            <p>For no man hath juſt reaſon to be angry, if Conſenters to that Order endeavour to promote amongſt themſelves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian knowledge with an holy Converſation, by building up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the antient Foundations; namely, the Holy Scriptures and Sound Antiquity, with their Primitive moſt prudent Reformation.</p>
            <p>I do not diſown it, that my endeavours in this diſcourſe are in part collined at the ſtopping the growth of rigid Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:
<pb facs="tcp:61103:3"/>But the means I uſe is only ſuch, as many conſiſt with Sincere and Chriſtian Charity to all Diſſenting Brethren, and a real deſire of their Peace:</p>
            <p>
               <q>And that which put me upon this undertaking was, a firm perſwaſion, that keeping up the Parochial Aſſemblies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (in that good Order and Unity, which the Goſpel of Chriſt and the Laws of the Kingdom require,) is one of our ſtrongeſt Fences and Securities againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, Strife, Uncharitableneſs, and other enemies of Sincere and Solid Chriſtianity: and that the Diſſipation and breaking of the Parochial Churches will prove the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down our walls, to bring in that <hi>Trojan Horſe,</hi> which our Gates are not wide enough to admit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But yet I freely declare (if the declaration of ſo mean a perſon be worth taking notice of by any) that it was far from my intendment in this work to endeavour to obſtruct any favours and relaxations, which may be thought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by our Governours to Pious and Peaceable Diſſenters, in order to their bringing them in (with fair ſalvoes to their Conſciences) to help with us to do the work of our Great Maſter with one heart and in one way.</p>
            <p>And certainly the breaking in of the Floods of ungodlineſs upon the Age and Nation, calls aloud for the uniting their and our ſtrengths, to bear up with arms and breaſts againſt them.</p>
            <p>And I am confident that my Propoſals in this Paper will not be found to inlarge the diſtances amongſt Brethren: For the removal of which, by pouring out upon us all a Spirit of Meekneſs, Love, and mutual Forbearance, I daily pray to the God of Mercy and Peace, which I beſeech him to grant, even in our days, if it be his bleſſed will, according to the unſpeakable riches of his mercy towards Sinners in Chriſt Jeſus our only Mediator and Saviour, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61103:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. I.</hi> An Account of the Nature of the Explicit Stipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation propoſed.</head>
            <p>THE Laws of this Land as well as the Inſtitutions of the Church, do ſuppoſe ſome Relation to intervene betwixt the Parochial Miniſters and the people of their ſeveral Pariſhes committed to their Charge.</p>
            <p>By a [Pariſh] I mean, a compaſs of Ground, containing in it ſuch a number of Chriſtian Inhabitants, as may Ordinarily aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at one place for publick worſhip, and who are, if duly qualified, obliged by Law ſo to Aſſemble for the celebration of all parts of publick worſhip.</p>
            <p>And not only by Law but by Scripture alſo, in which there is not one example to be found of a Chriſtian, who did cohabit with and among Chriſtians, and yet ordinarily at times of worſhip did ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from them, to go and aſſemble with other Chriſtians elſewhere.</p>
            <p>So that all Goſpel Aſſemblies for worſhip were <hi>Coetus Parochia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum,</hi> or <hi>Cohabitantium,</hi> who might be ready to obſerve and help one another, in relation both to temporal and ſpiritual wants and neceſſities.</p>
            <p>This Relation of the Miniſters of ſuch Parochial Congregations to their people, both obligeth and impowereth every ſuch Miniſter to diſpence the Word and Sacraments, and perform other Miniſterial duties, to all the People of his Pariſh, who are willing and duly qualified to receive them.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Relation inableth ſuch Pariſhioners to challenge at his hands the diſpenſation of the ſaid Ordinances to them, and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them ordinarily to receive the ſame from him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:61103:4"/>
And it is far from me to intimate by theſe Papers, that all or the greateſt part of the preſent Pariſh Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are unſucceſsful in their work, aſſigned to them by the Word of God and the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>For there are multitudes of Chriſtians who are ready to come forth and own it, <q>That God made uſe of the Miniſtry of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, to awaken them to a ſerious conſideration of the ſpiritual and eternal concernments of their ſouls, and to bring them to a right underſtanding and practice of Repentance towards God, and Faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to a conſtant exerciſe of Mortification both of carnal and worldly luſts, and to conſecrate themſelves intirely to live to the Glory of God their Maker and Saviour, and to devote themſelves to do or ſuffer any thing that may promote in themſelves or others the knowledge and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, the fear, truſt, and love of God, with delight in him (as our ſufficient portion) and ſubmiſſion to him as our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, with Faith and Hope, in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who of God is made unto us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And they will further teſtifie, that, by the Preaching and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Conforming Clergy, they were brought to imbrace an univerſal Charity towards all men, even enemies, and to take up a more ſpecial Love and Delight in all thoſe who own the fear of God, and adorn the Goſpel of Chriſt, by an holy, humble and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful converſation, yea though ſuch ſhould diſſent from them in the preſent minute differences about things Indifferent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If to be wrought up to this frame by the Spirit of God (who alone gives the increaſe, whoever endeavours to plant or water) be <hi>Converſion,</hi> Multitudes (to the praiſe of the Glory of the Grace of God) have been, and are daily Converted by the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet I apprehend, and ſhall endeavour to make it good in this preſent Eſſay, that not only the more immediate ends of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry would (probably) be more effectually promoted by ſuch an explicit Confeederation intervening betwixt the Parochial Miniſters and their people, but many other appendant advantages would thence refult to the whole body of the Nation, as I have inſinuated in my Title-page.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61103:4"/>
I preſume that all knowing Chriſtians will grant, that the ends wherefore Chriſt by his Apoſtles did inſtitute Miniſters in the Churches (I mean amongſt perſons already converted to the faith) were at leaſt theſe following, <q>That they might watch over the ſouls of their flocks, that they might adminiſter to them the Word and Sacraments, that they might in the name of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aſſembled with them, and with the concurrence of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts and mouths alſo, (at leaſt in ſaying <hi>Amen</hi>) offer up Confeſſion of Sins, Prayers, Praiſes and Thankſgivings in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſemblies; That they might Inſtruct, Admoniſh, Reprove and Comfort their People, as their condition ſhould require, and that not only in publick Preaching and Catechiſing, but in Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conference, and by teaching from Houſe to Houſe; That they might viſit the Sick, and promote the due relief and maintenance of the Poor of the Flock; That they might baptize the Children of Believers and Adult Perſons duly qualified, and that they might receive to the full Communion of the Church in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, ſuch Minor Members, as being baptized in their Infancy, are grown up to a due meaſure of the knowledge of God, and Chriſt, and his Goſpel, and are of unblameable lives, and do make ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn profeſſion to ſtand to their vow made in Baptiſm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That all theſe are duties incumbent upon Miniſters, even under the Parochial Form, I hope will be granted, and ſhall not trouble my Reader with a proof of them, till they are contradicted,</p>
            <p>And that no Law of the Land, or Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains any Parochial Miniſter from the faithful diſcharge of all thoſe duties, is undeniably evident, in that thoſe Laws confirm to Miniſters their ſetled Maintenance, for this very cauſe, that they might be encouraged to be faithful in the ſervice of God and of his Church, in the premiſed duties.</p>
            <p>And it is evident alſo, that the moſt Reverend Fathers of the Church (the Biſhops) would not only encourage Miniſters to be faithful herein (as ſome of us have found by addreſs to our pious and learned Dioceſans) but that they would alſo rejoyce over ſuch diligent and faithful Miniſters, and thank God for them, and make mention of them in their prayers without ceaſing.</p>
            <p>So that upon an impartial ſearch I believe it will be found, that one of the chiefeſt reaſons why this work is not done more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, is to be laid to the charge of Parochial Miniſters and their People.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61103:5"/>
And the greateſt hindrance of them in doing mutually their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties herein, will, I preſume, be found to be this, <q>Becauſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters enter upon their charge with ſo little of ſolemnity, and without ſuch particular application to the people at their entrance, as might advantage them in their future work.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For if we conſult common experience, we ſhall find that when any Perſons enter upon any Office of Truſt for others benefit, the want of due ſolemnity at their entrance, doth not only render them leſs careful to conſider and diſcharge their duty; but alſo thoſe, for whoſe benefit Officers are intruſted, are both leſs inclined to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them in the diſcharge of their Office, and more prone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumaciouſly to oppoſe and diſcourage their Officers, when they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt faithfully to do their duty.</p>
            <p>Now it is but a little engine, that I propoſe, as likely to remove this and other great weights and miſchiefs with, <q>Namely, that at every Miniſters entrance upon his charge, there ſhould paſs a ſolemn Stipulation and Promiſe betwixt him and his People; and the ſame ſhould alſo with all convenient ſpeed be ſolemnly made betwixt thoſe Miniſters (who are already ſetled in Pariſhes) and their People.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not be ſo preſumptuous as to impoſe upon any of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren any forms of my own deviſing: But yet that my Reader may clearly underſtand, what I aim at, it is neceſſary that I ſet down ſome form of words, which might be ſuitable for the tranſaction of that ſolemnity: Though I know that abler perſons will eaſily find more apt and more comprehenſive terms, than mine are.</p>
            <p>I will therefore ſuppoſe that ſome ſuch forms as theſe following may conveniently be deviſed for this buſineſs.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="priestly_oath">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>N. N.</hi> legally preſented, inſtituted and inducted into the Rectory (or Vicaridge) of <hi>N.</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>N.</hi> do ſolemnly promiſe in the preſence of God to the Pariſhioners of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>N.</hi> That during my legal imcumbency and poſſeſſion of the ſaid Rectory (or Vicaridge) I will through the Grace of God endeavour faithfully to diſcharge amongſt them and for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, the Miniſtry which I have received of the Lord: I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to them the Goſpel of the Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, and inſtruct them in the ſaving truths thereof, both by publick Preaching and Catechiſing, and by private conference, as I have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61103:5"/>opportunity: I will labour to ſecure them, from thoſe that would pervert them, to either ſins or errors; I will endeavour to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the weak, to comfort the diſconſolate, and to reform the diſorderly by admonition and reproof; or if any continue obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate after my private reproof, I will proceed in my endeavours for their reformation in ſuch effectual ways as the Goſpel of Chriſt and the Laws of the Land do warrant me to purſue: I will viſit their ſick, and endeavour that due proviſion be made for the Poor of the Pariſh, I will conſtantly at due periods of time (unleſs hindred by ſickneſs or other lawful impediments) admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter amongſt them the Sacraments, and other parts of publick worſhip according to the authorized forms of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> I will prepare their Children by Catechiſing, that they may be confirmed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſs (where ſuch confirmation can with due ſolemnity and conveniency be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained) or that they may be admitted to full communion with the Church in the Sacrament (commonly called the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) upon their ſerious profeſſion to ſtand to the Covenant, which they made in Baptiſm. And in my diſcharge of all this I ſhall ſubmit my ſelf to the overſight and guidance of the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſs.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Witneſs my Hand.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Pariſhioners may ſubſcribe ſome ſuch form as this.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="parishioners_oath">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>N. N.</hi> Inhabitant of the Pariſh of <hi>N.</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>N.</hi> do promiſe by the Grace of God to live as becomes the Goſpel, in charity with all men, and unity of more ſpecial love with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Catholick Church, that is, with all that profeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified: And that I will hold conſtant communion with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> that is, with all thoſe Chriſtian Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, who are united in the profeſſion of thoſe articles of Doctrine, and in the exerciſe of thoſe Forms of publick worſhip, and in ſubmiſſion to that Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical diſcipline that are agreeable to the Scriptures and owned by the Laws of this Realm: And I will generally and ordinarily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with the reſt of the Pariſhioners of <hi>N.</hi> aforeſaid, at the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church there, for the celebration of all parts of the eſtabliſhed publick worſhip by Mr. <hi>N. N.</hi> Rector or Vicar there, and that I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61103:6"/>will own the ſaid Mr. <hi>N. N.</hi> as my immediate Guide in ſpiritual things, under the inſpection of the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſs: And that I will attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Preaching of the Word, and Catechiſing, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments by the ſaid Mr. <hi>N. N.</hi> and ſubmit to his admonitions, and give him all due honour for his work ſake. And that I will readily and chearfully do my duty (as a fellow member of the ſame body) to all the Pariſhioners of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>N.</hi> in labouring to build them up in the moſt holy Faith, and in provoking them to love, and to good works, and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating to thoſe of them that ſhall need relief, according to that eſtate, which God hath or ſhall bleſs me with: And that I will mark thoſe who cauſe diviſions and avoid them: And that if I ſhall happen to remove my dwelling out of the Pariſh of <hi>N.</hi> aforeſaid, I will deſire and receive a Certificate from the Miniſter and Pariſhioners here, to the Miniſter and Pariſhioners of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, to which I ſhall remove (That I have lived in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, and with the Church of <hi>England</hi>) and I ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſire Letters of Commendation from the Miniſter and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners of this Pariſh, to the Miniſter and People of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to which I ſhall remove, requeſting them that they will receive me (with thoſe of my family that are qualified for it) to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them in Holy Worſhip: And I ſhall be ready to teſtifie by like ſolemn promiſe my readineſs to joyn in Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with that Miniſter and Parochial Congregation to whom I ſhall remove, as I did before with the Miniſter and People of this Pariſh of <hi>N.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Witneſs My Hand.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe or the like ſolemn promiſes do not (as far as I am able to apprehend) ſo much as ſhake one Pin in the preſent Fabrick of either Church or State: Nor in the Stipulation is there any thing promiſed by either the Miniſters or the People, but what I judge they are obliged already to do and execure by the general precepts of the Goſpel, or the Eccleſiaſtical Laws and Conſtitutions of this Realm, or Chriſtian Prudence, though they ſhould never make and ſubſcribe ſuch explicit promiſes as theſe are.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61103:6"/>
I am ſure that Miniſters oblige themſelves expreſly to all this at their Ordination, before the Biſhop, and Presbyters, and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation then aſſembled.</p>
            <p>And I eaſily grant that it is only matter of expedience and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (as Eccleſiaſtical affairs now ſtand in <hi>England</hi>) that this mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual covenanting ſhould be ſo expreſs and ſolemn (for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Peoples doing their mutual duties to one another as Offices of Relations, implies in both a Conſcience, that they are under an Obligation to one another, which may not improperly be called an implicit Covenanting:)</p>
            <p>And therefore if any man ſhall riſe up againſt theſe Papers, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt him to remember, <q>That the Controverſie betwixt us is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be only this, <hi>whether what he</hi> ſhall offer be in the ballance of Chriſtian prudence of more probability to promote thoſe great ends of piety and peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than this which I propoſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And if any can offer better Expedients, or ſhall evince that mine deſerve not to be eſteemed ſuch, I reſolve to be no Heretick in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks or Prudentials, deſiring in uprightneſs to be conformed to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s profeſſion to do all things for the truth, and nothing againſt it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I will labour to ſhew how uſeful this Order would be to the ends propoſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. II.</hi> The uſefulneſs of the Parochial Stipulation, to promote regularity of life in the Miniſters and their People, with Brotherly Love, and good Neighbourhood.</head>
            <p>IT is plain to every mans obſervation, that all the perſwaſives of men to any undertaking (whether by repreſenting the attempt as neceſſary, or beneficial, or honourable, or under any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects) have no longer force than they are kept preſent, and fixed in the mind and imagination of the Undertaker: So that when once thoſe arguments are ſlipt out of the thoughts, the attempt goes on very dully, becauſe promoted only by the habitual impreſſion, yet remaining upon the Phancy.</p>
            <p>The Solemnity therefore of this promiſe would ſix upon Miniſters ſuch a laſting and warm ſenſe of their duty, and ſo frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61103:7"/>their thoughts of it, as would not probably permit them eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to grow remiſs and inadvertent. For indeed the promiſe made to many, and before many witneſſes, would be apt to awaken in Miniſters a remembrance of their duty upon the very ſight of any of thoſe, to whom, and before whom they made their ingagement.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I trouble my Reader with a more large proof of that, which I think no man can deny, who is but Maſter of ſo much judgement and phancy as to preſent to his own imagination (as it were in different Scenes) One Perſon haſting and poſting to his Living as to a Preferment only, and another Perſon gravely and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately entring upon his imployment with ſuch ſolemn Application to the People as this we ſpeak of, <q>Letting them know, he comes amongſt them with a deſire and purpoſe, through Gods aſſiſtance, to ſerve to the Glory of God, and their edification in the truth, as it is in Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which of theſe two in any mans judgement, is likelieſt to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the work of his Office with the more vigorous diligence?</p>
            <p>Beſides, this very ſolemnity of entrance would give the Miniſter ſuch an eſteem with the people, as would highly advantage his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture diſcharges: For when themſelves had thus by Covenant received him, they would look upon him with all affectionate reſpects as their Guide, yea they would entertain him as an Angel of God.</p>
            <p>Whereas now, the People, till they have trial of us, keep at a diſtance, and are ſhy and jealous of us; and if after ſome time they find, that we are not proud and contentious, or ſtrict in looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our dues, many of them are not much further ſolicitous; inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating therein, that in the preſent ſtate of Pariſhes, <q>the care of many Pariſhioners is, rather to have a well-humour'd and quiet Neighbour, than an able and faithful Miniſter.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And there is no queſtion to be made, but that the like Poſtnate Solemnity would ſtrengthen the ſenſe of duty in us, who are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy entred upon our imployments, as that which is Preliminary would do to them that enter with it.</p>
            <p>And that alſo it would make our Miniſtry more acceptable and ſucceſsful for the future, is not to be doubted; Beſides, that this would influence the whole body of the Miniſters, to make them regular and exemplary in their converſation is a preſumption ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, that I need not ſtay to prove it. For no doubt Miniſters thus ſolemnly obliging themſelves to walk as Examples to their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61103:7"/>Flocks in all manner of holy Converſation, would both in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and prudence ſet a ſtrict guard both over their lives and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, remembring the [wo] due to them by whom offences do come.</p>
            <p>But I muſt further let my Reader know, that my projection is, not only, that this Stipulation ſhould once be ſolemny made, and never after be publickly Recognized, ſo that the Subſcriptions of Miniſters and People being locked up in the Pariſh-Cheſt, ſhould ſo remain till Worms and Moths had conſumed the Parchment or Paper:</p>
            <p>But this I think, may prudently and piouſly be done, further, namely that on the Lords day, before the day of the Celebration of the Communion (whether monthly, or quarterly, or after celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) the Miniſter ſhould after Evening Prayers recount before the people the promiſes mutually given, exhorting them to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and faithfully to fulfil the ſame, both towards him and towards one another, and the whole Church of God, and that he ſhould promiſe on his part with all fidelity, through the Grace of God to look to his diſcharge of his duty to them.</p>
            <p>Next, let us conſider what are likely to be the effects of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant amongſt the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it would promote holineſs of Converſation amongſt them, is warrantably inferred, both becauſe the Miniſters oblige themſelves to a more ſpecial and particular care of every ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Flock, and they of the Flock are obliged to a mutual care of one another, and every one by this Covenant, obligeth himſelf ſincerely to endeavour to walk as becomes the Goſpel; And this particularity of relation, by ſolemn promiſe interceeding betwixt the Miniſter and them, would put the Miniſter on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and private applications by way of inſtruction or admonition, which have their effect ordinarily beyond the general declarations of the truths of the Goſpel, in Catechiſing, or Preaching, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reprehenſions of vices in ſuch publick diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>Beſides, they would be under a conſtant expectancy that upon their irregularity they ſhould be dealt with after our Saviours Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. And that when they had been perſonally and privately admoniſhed, and did not reform, they ſhould be notified to the Congregation, and upon further obſtinacy be preſented to thoſe publick Eccleſiaſtical Officers, who are impowred by Law
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61103:8"/>to take congnizance of the ſame. And that ſuch Preſentments would not end, only in paying the fees of the Court, and ſome Commutation mony there: Nor could they imagine, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregation to whom the Offence and Scandal was given, ſhould never inquire what is done upon the preſentment, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſatisfaction from the offending party, before they received them to Communion again; And we may reaſonably preſume that all the pious Fathers of the Church, the Biſhops with the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Officers under them, would take care that ſuch ſatisfaction ſhould be given by the Delinquent: And none of this would bring any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> innovation or alteration in Church affairs.</p>
            <p>And further that hereby the people would be ſpirited to a free and Chriſtian Nieghbourhood amongſt themſelves is not at all to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſeeing it is the Ordinary Conſequence of Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to give to the Combined a mutual kindneſs and confidence to, and in, one another.</p>
            <p>Nay more, whereas all other combinations that are made on the principles of univerſal and Catholick recuſancy of Communion with other Chriſtians (and there are more Catholick Recuſants in <hi>England</hi> than Papiſts) do narrow mens affections towards others, and cauſe them to malign, cenſure, damn and deſpiſe thoſe (who are not of their own bran and leaven) it may juſtly be hoped that this coalition and combinement, founded on the truly Catholick Principles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (which unchurcheth not nor reprobateth Chriſtians of any form, that hold repentance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) would give ſuch an impreſſion of humility and charity to all the Pariſhioners, as that the Diſſenters themſelves ſhould find the bleſſed and benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent warmth and influence of it, whilſt we endeavour to live in the exerciſe of Charity and mutual good offices with all conſcientious Diſſenters, and follow peace both amongſt our ſelves and with all men.</p>
            <p>One thing more I hope I may mention without raiſing the ſcorn of any ſorts of Readers, namely, <q>That in proceſs of time this procedure would not only reform ſcandalous Miniſters, but ſcandalous Livings alſo: I mean thoſe poor Livings (as they are called) upon which even a frugal perſon cannot live, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide things honeſt in the ſight of all men for himſelf and for his family.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61103:8"/>
Which were not indeed ſo poorly endowed Originally, but firſt by the Popes Appropriations of the great Tithes, to Orders of Monks and Nuns, and after by the Impropriations of the ſame by King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the 8th. to Lay-men, and by other incroachments of the Laiety both in pretended Preſcriptions and ſeveral other wayes (not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per here to be reckoned up) many Pariſh-Church is (eſpecially in Cities and Corporations) are d prived of a due maintenance for the Miniſters: And Religion thereby receives as much damage, as by almoſt any one of Satans later projects againſt the ſame. Againſt which I propoſe this Parochial Stipulation, as a Remedy very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to be effectual; for undoubtedly the Combined Pariſhioners would by the permiſſion of thoſe in Authority, and by the aſſiſtance of pious Patrons either buy in Impropriated Tithes, or raiſe an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable maintenance for their Miniſter ſome other way.</p>
            <p>I will add further, That whereas now upon the decay of ſtrength in aged Miniſters, the People are left too oft only to the guidance of a Curate, that is of ſmall abilities and ſmall allowance, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Livings will not afford better Salaries (if a competency be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to them who have ſpent their time and ſtrength amongſt the People:) We may warrantably hope, that the people of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Combination, will neither be ſo ungrateful to him who hath faithfully laboured amongſt them, as to urge a larger allowance from him than his income will bear, nor will they be ſo unconcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their own ſouls, as to forbear to raiſe by contribution a fit allowance for an able Aſſiſtant.</p>
            <p>I will add this further, That it cannot be feared that People thus ingaged will permit that the Pariſh Clarks ſhould be licentious Ale-Drapers or otherwiſe looſe or vain perſons. But they will require that they be of a prudent and inoffenſive Converſation: The like care we may hope that the Pariſhoners and Miniſters would take about the Election of perſons prudent and conſcientious, to diſcharge the Offices of Churchwardens and Sidesmen, and not ſuffer theſe Offices to go by Houſe-row, and be laid upon the ſhoulders of thoſe, who know neither the importance of their Office, nor the nature or ſenſe of the Oaths they are required to take.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61103:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Expediency of the Parochial Stipulation to reduce Diſſenters to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, and ſecure thoſe, who at preſent do Conform, from falling away.</head>
            <p>IF there be any conſolations in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any Bowels and mercies, Thoſe Chriſtians moſt taſte of the ſweetneſs thereof, who ſtrive to preſerve the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and rejoyce over all impartially that own the fear of God, and the faith of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: and who can according to the dictates of Catholick Charity <hi>and Evangelical Love (truly ſo called)</hi> freely joyn in all acts of holy Communion, with any Chriſtians amongſt whom their lot is caſt to be, where the Communion is not clogged with urged compliance to ſinful things, and who do not obſtruct others coming into Communion with themſelves by any ſinful or unneceſſary requirements.</p>
            <p>And it is no difficulty to prove that this propenſity to <hi>Catholick Communion</hi> is the healing temper under which alone the Chriſtian world may hope to obtain again that peace and unit, the bleſſed warmth whereof made the Primitive Churches to flouriſh.</p>
            <p>And it is no leſs eaſily evinced that Catholick Recuſancy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with others, is that narrow engine wherewith the Devil hath cramped and tormented the Churches of Chriſt in theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages; and that from thence came Fire and Faggot, Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Proſcriptions, civil broils, and the reſt of the miſchiefs which have made Chriſtian Kingdoms miſerable through the ſeveral Sects purſuance of their Religious differences, with more bitterneſs than they would have done Mahumetiſm it ſelf.</p>
            <p>On which account we can juſtly arraign ſeveral amongſt us for as very Catholick Recuſants, or (which is all one) for as Univerſal Refuſers of Communion with other Chriſtians as any Papiſts, yea, or Ruſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61103:9"/>
But it is evident to all impartially obſervant, that a more humble and charitable Spirit acted the Church of <hi>England</hi> at her Primitive Reformation.</p>
            <p>And I hope that this Explicit Combination in her Parochial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies pleaded for, will not make any ſuſpect that a leſs inlarged temper is hereby deſigned to be promoted, ſeeing the firſt part of promiſe is, of holding Communion with all Chriſtians: And we all proteſt to take all for Brethren who hold Chriſt as the foundation, and walk by the rule of the New Creature, and we pray for peace on them, and on the Iſrael of God.</p>
            <p>But alas this Candor of ours is made ineffectual to keep even all our flocks in their folds through a late complotment of ſome, who, though not intentionally, yet will be found, I fear, eventually to play the Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers, and plane the way for the reentrance of the moſt notorious ſort of Catholick Recuſancy.</p>
            <p>For it is eaſie to obſerve that the great allurement of our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to turn aſide to the Tents of our Companions is, that ſuch ſeem through their mutual ingagements, to take thoſe that unite to them under a more ſpecial care, for both their temporal and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual concernments.</p>
            <p>Will it then be imprudent to uſe ſome of the Viper in our Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, or to cleave the Wood with a Wedge of its own?</p>
            <p>When therefore it ſhall appear, that we with no leſs ſolemnity or ſincerity, oblige our ſelves ſo to take care for all of ours, yea and ſtill to let our Fountain of Brotherly Love run over, and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed in the ſtreets to all others that are Chriſtians, I am apt to think (and it may be moſt of my unprejudiced Readers will be of my mind) that it will be a more effectual courſe to reduce Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters than all diſputes (though evincing with the cleareſt evidence the ſinfulneſs of Separation) have been able to do; and as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod eat up the Rods of the Magicians, the Combination of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Parochial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies thereof, would do little leſs to moſt other unwarranted Combinations amongſt us.</p>
            <p>For when once the Sober and Conſcientious Diſſenters ſhall be convinced, that all prudent and ſaithful care is taken, to purge out all leaven of malice and wickedneſs out of our Parochial Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and that they may in thoſe Aſſemblies have green paſtures and ſtill waters alſo, and that Miniſters are ingaged and excited to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61103:10"/>purſue the edification of their people in faith and holineſs, then, and not till then it may be hoped, that many pious and humble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt them will in a ſmall time fall in with publick Order.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that none of thoſe who are departed from our Church ſhould be reduced to the fold again, yet if this Parochial Covenant were ſetled, it would at leaſt ſecure to us, thoſe that at preſent do hold Communion with us, and bind them up ſo cloſe and compact that no more could drop out.</p>
            <p>We are not ignorant, that when God hath ſo far proſpered our Miniſtry and Labours in diligent Catechiſing and Preaching and other faithful endeavours, <q>That any inconſiderate and ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have been awakened by us to ſearch and try their hearts, and waies and turn unto the Lord;</q> as ſoon I ſay as ſuch are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be grown ſerious in the frame of their Spirits, and regular in their Coaverſation, preſently they are aſſaulted by ſome Seducer to make one turn further,</p>
            <p>
               <q>And he ſuggeſts to them, that it is not enough that they have taken God for their God, and Chriſt for their Saviour by ſerious and reſolved choice and purpoſe of heart, that they have an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal charity for all men, and ſpecial Brotherly-Love unto the Brethren (for all this they were brought to by our Miniſtry) but as if theſe were the <hi>primar</hi> and rudiments of Chriſtianity, they are tempted to remove from under our Miniſtry, who called them into the grace of God, unto another Goſpel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But the Parochial Stipulation would be an excellent fence againſt theſe Seducers: becauſe our people then would let us know, that they are tempted, and would think themſelves bound to do ſo, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken us for their Guides by Explicit Contract.</p>
            <p>Whereas now (alas) many are turned Renegado's from the Church beyond recovery, and the Miniſter, it may be, is the laſt man in the Pariſh that hears of it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is not to be doubted, but that ſome or other of their honeſt Neighbours, combined in the ſame Promiſes with them, would take the Alarm, and think themſelves obliged to ſtep in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and endeavour to prevent their falling away, by applying the beſt arguments and counſel they could uſe, and would alſo timely inform the Miniſter and Congregation of the danger of one of the Flock.</p>
            <p>Beſides our arguments, that then we ſhould uſe for their confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61103:10"/>in the Unity of the Church, would be ſeriouſly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially conſidered, whereas now, they either do not regard us, or ſoon admit the ſuſpicion inſtilled by deceitful workers (that we ſeek theirs, not them.)</p>
            <p>But after this mutual contract hath made them ſecure, that it is our care of them only that calls us to their help, we may more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perſwade them impartially to conſider both our arguments, and the diſcourſes written by pious and learned men, in vindication of communion with us, and for the cure of Church Diviſions.</p>
            <p>Add to this, that it is more than probable that all the Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the league, would be very careful to ſtudy how to defend their own Conformity to the Orders and Conſtitutions Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal by Law eſtabliſhed, and would ſtand more zealouſly for the Credit of the ſame, than now many of them think themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do.</p>
            <p>For it is obvious to obſerve, that ſcarce a Separatiſt can be met with, but is taught (like one brought up in the School of War and Contention) to ſay more by way of cavilling againſt the publick Settlement, and our Communion therein, than one in twenty of our Lay-Conformiſts can ſay for it, becauſe indeed they do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern themſelves in the ſtudy of thoſe truths by which our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the ſetled Order is juſtified.</p>
            <p>But this explicit Covenant would make them think they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in honour to be able to plead for their way.</p>
            <p>And beſides it would urge Miniſters to maintain both publick and private conferences with their people about Church Order and other matters of Religion, and Conferences are but Catechiſing the Elder ſort, as Catechiſing is conference with the Younger.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if either this or ſome other courſe be not taken to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and quicken the Parochial Miniſters and their Congregations jointly to endeavour either the reforming or elſe the putting away from among themſelves the ſcandalous and notoriouſly vitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to unite thoſe who do yet own the ſetled Order, and to fortifie them in the truth and obedience to the ſame, we ſhall ſoon find that not only the Sectarian Catholick Recuſant on the one ſide, and the Popiſh Catholick Recuſant on the other will daily get upon us, and if our banks and ſhores be not better fortified, thoſe two working Seas will eat our Iſland quite through, but alſo that prophaneſs will prevail and overſpread us as a Leproſie, which is moſt of all to be dreaded.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61103:11"/>
And whether of thoſe two Catholick Recuſants, I mean, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Romiſh or the complicated Sectarian will prevail againſt the other, and keep the field, if once the Church of <hi>England</hi> be diffol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (which hath always been terrible to the Romaniſts as an Army with Banners) is not difficult to foreſee.</p>
            <p>For how can the ſeveral little bodies and ſects, into which the other Diſſenters, from the Engliſh Proteſtantiſm, will be crumbled by diviſion upon diviſion, be able long to bear up againſt that united intereſt, which the fine and ſubtile Romaniſts will obtain in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, acting in part under the Vizor of other Sects, partly wearing their own profeſſion openly.</p>
            <p>For it is eaſie to obſerve how their Emiſſaries (according to inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) ſeek another manner of Quarry, &amp; fly at another ſort of Game, when they appear as Romaniſts, than that which ſome of the other ſects do follow; They ſtrive not ſo much to ingage Meticulous Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Women and Mechanicks, or narrow ſpirited Melancholiſts, or Opinionative Burgers and Traders, theſe the Romiſh Fiſhermen ſeek not after, but if any ſuch come to their Net, they caſt them not away.</p>
            <p>But their moſt taking Arts are laid out for the inveigling young and pregnant Wits in the Univerſities or elſewhere, who may be trained up to write Polemicks, and practiſe Politicks, and to ingage Perſons of Honour and Intereſt amongſt the Nobility and Gentry (not mattering what their Morals are) who are likely to be of great importance in the legal alteration or ſettlement of a Nation: and thoſe whom they have gained in their concealed and by-trade as Undertakers and Brokers for other Sects, they will eaſily turn over into their great bank, when they find it ſeaſonable to unmask themſelves.</p>
            <p>And this Myſtery of iniquity hath been, and is ſtill working, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which hath letted will lett, till it is taken out of the way, namely, the legal eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> owned by his ſacred Majeſty and the Laws.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61103:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> The Expediency of the Explicit Promiſes to ſecure publick Peace.</head>
            <p>THat the publick Peace of Nations is the moſt valuable temporal bleſſing that men enjoy, is without diſpute: And that the peace of <hi>England</hi> would be in a great meaſure ſecured by this Parochial Covenant may eaſily be evidenced.</p>
            <p>For firſt, the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth ſo influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence all that are Genuine Sons thereof, as renders them the beſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the World, and makes them obey the King and the Laws for Conſcience ſake in all lawful things, and reſtrains from reſiſtance on any account (civil or religious) leſt they ſhould receive to themſelves damnation.</p>
            <p>Whether any of the Catholick Recuſants, whether Romiſh or otherwiſe Sectarians be ſo diſpoſed to Obedience to Authority, let their own Writings and Practiſes witneſs in the Gate, for it is not agreeable to the peaceable deſign of theſe Papers to queſtion other mens Loyalty, who own Religion under any form.</p>
            <p>But the Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have givne ſufficient evidence, that in Conſcience of their Allegiance by Law required, they will not only not reſiſt, but if occaſion be, they will fight for their Soveraign and the eſtabliſhed Laws, and venture life and eſtate in that juſt Service.</p>
            <p>And if their own ſins and the ſins of the Nation render their arms ſucceſleſs, they will not only pray ſtill for their Soveraign, but ſuffer with him, yea though they ſhould know beforehand that <hi>Zibah</hi> (the falſe Informer) ſhould keep half ſequeſtred <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheths</hi> eſtate, even after our Lord the King was returned in peace.</p>
            <p>So that his Majeſty might be aſſured that this Parochial Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would give the Royal Intereſt the ſtrongeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooting in the hearts of his ſubjects.</p>
            <p>But beſides this way of ſecuring publick peace, by right princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling the Subjects, the Parochial Covenant would do much alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards prevention of rebellion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61103:12"/>
For it is no ſmall advantage to Governours, in order to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of ſeditions to know beforehand from what quarter they are moſt likely to riſe and blow.</p>
            <p>And without all doubt, it a new Civil War ſhould ſpring up in <hi>England</hi> in our daies (which God in mercy prevent) his Majeſty might have the Muſter-roles of his Enemies, by requiring the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of them, who in the ſeveral Pariſhes becauſe of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs are refuſed, or through other pretences do refuſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine in Conformity.</p>
            <p>But yet far be it from me, to deſign to intimate, that the Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Diſſenters would make the main body and bulk of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Army, or would be the head and contrivers of the War; there are amongſt them unqueſtionably many who fear God and the King.</p>
            <p>But we have rather reaſon to ſuſpect (that as it was in our late troubles) the main Contrivers of a War would be prophane and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Politicians; men of the Leviathan-faith (or rather Infidelity) who worſhip not God but Intereſt, and are men of this world only, and reckon nothing Sacred in Government, but the prevalency of Power, which Sacredneſs they know may be preſently vacanted by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of a greater oppoſite Power, if they can work themſelves up to it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the men who uſe to contrive and begin troubles in all States and Kingdoms, and (to drive on their deſignes) uſe the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous zeal of perſons Don-Quixotted in Religion, by raiſing in them fanciful fears and jealouſies that their <hi>Diana</hi> is in danger.</p>
            <p>However I am ſure that none of the Church of <hi>England</hi> could imbark in a war againſt their Governour for the alteration of the Laws by force of Arms, whithout renouncing their Principles.</p>
            <p>And if Piety and Orderly Converſation with Loyalty and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity be happily promoted by this ſo probable means of the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Stipulation, I hope many upright perſons amongſt them of the Separation will come in and joyn with us: And thereby I am ſure they would ſilence the importunate calls of them, who require pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick teſtification of their Repentance, for being ingaged in hoſtility formerly againſt their Soveraign and his Laws: Their return to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Conformity to the Eſtabliſhed Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, was a ſufficiently ſignal declaration of their return to Loyalty.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61103:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. V.</hi> The Expediency of the Parochial Stipulation, to make proviſion for the Poor, and increaſe Trade amongſt us.</head>
            <p>NO rational perſon can think but that the infinitely wiſe and good God hath made diſtribution of the riches of this world (the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs or inequality) to ſome men a greater, to ſome a leſſer portion, for the exerciſe of his graces in all; that from every outward ſtate there may be a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the eternal habitations; whilſt the Brethren of high degree teſtifie their gratitude to God, and their love to him and his Chriſt in his poor members by their bounty; And the Brethren of low degree teſtifie their humility and ſubmiſſion to God and dependance upon him; and ſo the abundance of the Charitable rich, and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of the pious poor, conſpire into one excellent harmony of many thankſgivings from both of them unto the infinitely good God, who filleth all with his plenty.</p>
            <p>But though our Lord hath declared, that it is more bleſſed to give than to receive, and God hath promiſed repayment in good meaſure, preſſed down, ſhaken together, and running over, to the chearful giver; yet we find that the ſpring of moſt mens Charity runs very ſlow and narrow, or elſe, through miſtake, is derived into a wrong Channel.</p>
            <p>Here therefore I offer as an expedient in this caſe the Parochial Covenant; For every one of the combination would look upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as obliged, not only by duty (as Gods Steward of what he had received) but by ſpecial relation alſo to contribute freely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the relief of all the poor and indigent of the Society, which himſelf is a member of, yea and to the poor of other Chriſtian Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, (as members with him of the Catholick Church of Chriſt) if there be need, and occaſion be offered him.</p>
            <p>And beſides, every member of the Society would imploy his brain as well as his purſe, for the ſervice of the Brotherhood, in contriving
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61103:13"/>how all the honeſt members of the body might be ſet on work, and learn (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth) to maintain good works for neceſſary uſes: So that herery every Pariſh would become a kind of Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, wherein ſome uſeful manufacture or other would be ſet on foot. And all the little Trades and Ingenuities of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> would be tranſplanted into this Iſland, and improved (as uſually the inventions of other Nations are by the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) to the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Nation. And whereas now (to the detriment of the whole Kingdom) the traffick of ſome of the moſt important Trades, is in a manner ingroſſed by Diſſenters (and it is a great temptation to men of Craf. and Ingenuity to turn Sectaries, whilſt they ſee, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence fo Scruples gets an opinion of their honeſty and brings in cuſtom) then the Trade would become more diffuſed, and a fit and equal ſhare therein would be put into the hands of Conſcientious and Loyal Conformiſts, whoſe integrity (by this publick Teſt of a whole Pariſh owning them as members) would be with good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage repreſented to thoſe they ſhould deal with.</p>
            <p>And hereby alſo the Biſhops, and the Parochial Miniſtry under them, would have the advantage to ingage the Contribution of their richer Pariſhioners, for the education of Youths of pregnant and hopeful parts at School, and afterwards at the Univerſities (whoſe friends are not able to give them that breeding;) as alſo for diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of other poor Children to honeſt Trades. And both the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and the People combined would be ingaged to look after eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of their Members, <q>That they did bring up their Children in the fear and nurture of the Lord, and in ſome honeſt Calling, and that themſelves walked before their Children as examples of Chriſtian Converſation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which without all peradvanture would be the moſt effectual courſe, that ever yet was taken, to cure <hi>England</hi> of that lowſie diſeaſe, which at preſent it is infeſted with, I mean, a numerous Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vagrant ſturdy beggars; who throng ſo thick at the doors of the good Yeomen of the Nation, that they are certainly the greateſt oppreſſion which the Houſholders in the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt</hi> parts of the Nation do groan under.</p>
            <p>For I am confident to aſſert, as knowing that I ſpeak the words of truth and ſoberneſs, that many Houſekeepers in thoſe parts do expend twice as much yearly in alms to thoſe Vagrants (if that dole be worthy to be called alms) as they pay in all ſort of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61103:13"/>Taxes, and Layes, and Duties to the King, to the Church, and to the Poor of their own Pariſh: Nay, it is not to be doubted, but that that which his Majeſties ſubjects give to ſturdy Vagrants yearly, would Build, and Rigg, and furniſh out at leaſt ten gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Ships of War in any one year, or rather would build ſufficient Workhouſes, and provide ſufficient Stock to ſet all our poor on work in ſome manufactures about thoſe commodities, that are of Engliſh growth, and may be exported to the great advantage of the Nation.</p>
            <p>But when once Pariſhioners are thus embodied by their Covenant, they will eaſily be convinced, that they have fitter Objects for their Charity amongſt themſelves and other Chriſtian Societies, than ſuch ſlaves of luſt and idleneſs as our Vagrants are, and by degrees that miſtaken Charity of Relieving ſuch will grow out of faſhion, being ſwallowed up by that true and warrantable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the poor members of their own and other Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; And hereby the Erraticks would be forced to become fixed in their abode, and to endeavour to live like men, if not like Chriſtians alſo.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But this deſign in ſome meaſure now manifeſted to be like to produce ſuch a general benefit, may be objected againſt as impracticable, by reaſon of the weakneſs of the preſent Miniſtry of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>few of which are equal as to parts and prudence for the management of ſuch a work as this is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> My anſwer is very ſhort and peremptory, if I only ſay, then let them be deprived of their places, and more able Perſons put in their rooms.</p>
            <p>But I rather anſwer, that notwithſtanding the ſlanderous inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſome prophane Droles and other malignants, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to aſſert, <q>That there are not many of the Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (and indeed it is not fit there ſhould be any) who are not able from the Scriptures of the New and Old Teſtament, to prove unto the People their miſery both of guilt and impotency in their lapſed ſtate: And that God hath ſealed a New Covenant in the blood of Chriſt, wherein he hath promiſed through the propitiation of that blood, to forgive and blot out the ſins of the penitent believer, and to give grace and power to reſiſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61103:14"/>on thoſe that are ſincere and humble, and ſmother not, or ſtifle their convictions, and to increaſe Grace from Chriſts fulneſs, to the ſincere and diligent, and to ſecure by his Grace the humble and the watchful, that they ſhall not fall away; and that finally he will give to them (who by patient continuance in well doing, ſeek for honour, and glory, and immortality) eternal life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not alſo but that they are able from the Scriptures to prove the contrary threatnings, namely, <q>That they who reſiſt Gods Spirit in its motions and convictions (ſinning againſt their light) are in danger to be given over to a reprobate ſenſe, and to be eſtranged wholly from the life of God through a blinded mind, and hardned heart, and that the Impenitent and Unbelievers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſuch, ſhall periſh in their ſins, and that he who uſeth not his talents, is like to loſe them, and that he who truſts to an old age repentance, or a death-bed change, is in danger to be cut off in his ſins for combring the ground: And that there is unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable and everlaſting indignation and wrath, tribulation and anguiſh certainly to come on all thoſe who obey not the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, and die in a ſtate of impenitency and unbelief.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I do not queſtion alſo, but that moſt of the Engliſh Clergy are furniſhed with ability to prove the equity, beauty, and real plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and benefit of all the holy precepts of the Goſpel, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them, not only from the direct teſtimony and aſſertion of the Scriptures, but alſo by rational appeals to the light and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of thoſe of their Auditors, who have not loſt that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcitive power of their ſouls, whereby their ſpiritual ſenſe diſcerns betwixt good and evil: which power whoever hath loſt, is not far from the condition of the damned ſpirits, for he alſo is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the chains of darkneſs to the judgement of the great day, if God do not in a miracle of mercy break through that darkneſs, wherein the reſolved ſinner hath ſhut up himſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Such duties are theſe, to love God with all our heart, and to delight our ſelves in the manifeſtation of his glory by Jeſus Chriſt, and to love our Neighbour as our ſelves, to forgive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, to compaſſionate and help them who are miſerable, either by reaſon of ſin, or outward affliction, to delight in thoſe who are holy upon earth, and to mortifie and crucifie worldly and carnal luſts, and chearfully to bear the Croſs when we ſuffer for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61103:14"/>
               <q>I doubt not alſo but they can from Scripture, and from the like rational applications and appeals prove the real danger, unſeemli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unprofitableneſs of every ſin, with the real damage that ſinners ſuffer by ſin, eſpecially in their ſouls, being thereby eſtranged from the life of God and more indiſpoſed than before the perpetration of it, to the reverence, love, and delight, and confidence in God, which is the life and happineſs of all rational ſpirits.</q> I doubt not, I ſay, but moſt Miniſters can prove this alſo, to the conviction of them who will ponder and conſider the ſad influences of their own ſins, and have not ſinned away the ability of taſting the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come.</p>
            <p>I do not know that I have ſet down, either in the promiſes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, or threatnings, any, but what is neceſſary to be known by all who live under the means of grace, even by Lay-men.</p>
            <p>And if a Parochial Miniſter hath a competent knowledge of theſe truths, and can make them out to the conviction and inſtruction of honeſt plain men, <hi>who deſire to know what they muſt do to be ſaved,</hi> and if withal, the Teacher himſelf be of an holy, humble and ſober converſation, he is not to be judged unfit for the Miniſtry, becauſe he hath not ſtudied the Mathematicks, or Modern Politicks, or cannot humour his Diſcourſes to the pleaſing of their Guſto, who go to the Theater with greater devotion than they do to the Church, and prefer a modern and modiſh Play ſtuft with that they call wit, namely, interlardings of prophaneſs and ſcurrility, far before a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſeaſonable, but plane Sermon.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If it be objected further, that every Miniſter that is able to Preach and inſtruct plain men, is not able to manage the guidance of a Parochial Congregation, wherein may be perſons of great learning, and parts, and quality, the Nobility, Gentry, Lawyers and Phyſicians of the Nation, and can any imagine that theſe will ſubject themſelves by explicit Promiſe, to the overſight of the Parochial Clergy, many of which want both experience and prudence to rule their own Houſes well, how ſhall they then take care of the Houſe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61103:15"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer, that ſuppoſing thoſe Perſons of great abilities and qualities to be Chriſtians and Proteſtants, they will think it agreeable to Scripture and reaſon, to put themſelves into the ſociety of thoſe Chriſtians, amongſt whom they do cohabit for the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of publick worſhip adminiſtred by ſome perſon ſet apart to that office according to the Order of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>If then they own themſelves for members of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in their particular Pariſh Aſſemblies, their quality and abilities do not exempt them from owning the Pariſh Miniſter as their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Paſtor.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, their better abilities oblige them to give ſo much more aſſiſtance, and incouragement to him in his work. And ſo the Miniſter who was not equal to the guidance of a Pariſh in the ſingle ſtrength of his own prudence, will by the advice and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of ſuch helps in Government be rendred more able and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in his work.</p>
            <p>And an humble and modeſt Miniſter cannot want help ſufficient from God, to make his work proſperous, if he be ſincere in aiming at Gods Glory, and the good of his people. And if through pride and ſelf-willedneſs, any balk the advice of worthy and able Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, let complaint be made to the Lord Biſhop for his regulation: And indeed ſo little of Government is betruſted to the Pariſh Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that they can hardly miſcarry for want of political gifts, if they be worthy to be betruſted with the Preaching of the Word, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Beſides, amongſt us all, the Parochial Aſſemblies are under the guidance and inſpection of the moſt Reverend Fathers, the Biſhops of the ſeveral Dioceſſes: to queſtion whoſe equality to ſuch a work, will ill become any Member of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One conſideration more I muſt take leave to add as a Motive to all the Layety, to wiſh well to this propoſal of mine, namely, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhall be ſtrongly ſecured of continual love and peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves and their Miniſters.</p>
            <p>For after this Mutual Stipulation, the Generality of themſelves will of courſe, and in all reaſon ought to be, both Arbitrators and Judges of moſt differences that can poſſibly ariſe betwixt any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons of them and their Miniſters about Legal dues or otherwaies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61103:15"/>
And the Patrons, with others of the Nobility and Gentry, will have their juſt Eſteem and Authority in their Pariſhes hereby inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for whilſt they as Stars of the firſt Magnitude by their eminent Quality and Prudence, have chiefeſt influence upon Miniſters, both by way of Incouragement, Direction and Incitement of them to do their duty, they will raiſe a greater veneration of themſelves, both with Miniſters and Pariſhioners, and make all of them ready to exhibit on all occaſions affectionate devotions to the ſervice of ſuch their Benefactors, and their Generous Families.</p>
            <p>If then (as I have endeavoured to make good) the natural Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of this Parochial Explicit Stipulation appear likely to be theſe, The advance of Honour and Authority to our Grandees, of Holineſs and Diligence in our Miniſters, of Love and Unity amongſt the People, and of Loyalty towards our Gracious Soveraign in all his Subjects, I will promiſe my ſelf, that neither the Obſcurity of my ſelf the Propoſer, nor my mean way of managing this excellent Argument, will at all prejudice my Propoſal with true Engliſh Proteſtants.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>And now I certifie my Reader, that I have provided anſwers to all the other material Objections that I was able to foreſee might be made againſt this innocent and harmleſs Project, whether taken from the manner of Miniſters legal entrance by the preſentations of Patrons, or from the preſent Legally eſtabliſhed Order of Publick Worſhip, or the Miniſters maintenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But conſidering the preſent Criſis of affairs, and that it may be part of the ſubject of the queſtion in ſome of theſe Objections may either be taken away or altered, I thought it beſt to ſuppreſs them, that my Reader might be but little further troubled, than in a bare proſpect of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal; which his own thoughts, I believe, will commend to his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, but only thoſe in Authority can command to our practiſe.</p>
            <p>At whoſe feet I humbly lay down theſe my endeavours to ſerve God and my Country, and hope they will not reckon it preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in me thus to propoſe, ſeeing in a general danger of an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion every man runs with the beſt materials and inſtruments that he hath, to aſſiſt at ſtrengthning the banks.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61103:16"/>
And ſeeing alſo that I offer nothing to their conſideration, but what doth every way comport with the good Laws already made, or to be made by them, and which my juſt fears of the prevailing of bold impieties, as well as of the attempts of the enemies of our Church, have drawn me to make this publick.</p>
            <p>I ſhall promiſe my ſelf therefore, that all the pious Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will not only make a favourable conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my deſign but promote it by as advantageous a repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to thoſe in Authority, as it is capable of in truth and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And I hope my Nonconforming Brethren will not think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged on any account, to endeavour to obſtruct what I have repreſented thus uſeful and beneficial to us, and no way prejudicial to them: I never intended by making it manifeſt, that all this might be done, without violation of any part of the legal ſettlement, to upbraid them, who avouch that they cannot effectually promote faith and holineſs, without moving excentrically to the Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
            <p>For I believe, if they had the ſame apprehenſions of Conformity, which I at preſent have, they would come in and build with us.</p>
            <p>Much leſs did I intend, (as I again proteſt in the preſence of the All-ſeeing God) to fix the diſtance betwixt Conformiſts and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts by this propoſal.</p>
            <p>For I ſhall be far from repining, if thoſe in Authority think fit to remove any thing which may be laid aſide without caſting reproach on the Parochial Churches conforming to the preſent legal eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, or hindring their edification, and without giving ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to Foraign Churches, or prejudicing Catholick Communion with them.</p>
            <p>And as I queſtion not, but that all Momentous Conſtitutions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to thoſe good purpoſes, will be ſecured to us by the Piety and Prudence of the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, who is a true Nurſing Father to the Church, and through the advice of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament (being a Conſtellation of as eminent Patriots as any Age of our Forefathers ſaw ever imbodied on the account of the great truſt laid upon them) ſo, if they ſee fit, to diſpenſe in other things of meaner concernment, whereby Sober and Pious Diſſenters may imbody with us, I ſhall not be wanting to appear amongſt thoſe, who will teſtifie their joy for the healing of our breaches: nor ſhall I think my own ſhoe pincheth me becauſe my Brothers ſteps are more inlarged.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61103:16"/>
However, I hope that all amongſt us, and amongſt them alſo, who would rejoyce over the Churches of Chriſt, beholding their Order and Stedfaſtneſs, will eaſily unite in this prayer to the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the Sheep, <q>That he will continue and ſtrengthen amongſt us his ſtaves of bands and of beauty, that if ever the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> ſhall attempt to come into our Land, or tread in our Palaces, we may be able to raiſe up againſt him ſeven Shepheards, and eight Principal men.</q> And let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Glory be to God on high, on earth peace, good will amongſt men.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
